<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>How does JPA Security work internally?</title>
  <para>
    JPA Security intercepts your action with the <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>.
    Whenever you retrieve an entity from your <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>,
    it is subsidized by a proxy from JPA Security. Likewise whenever you perform a JPQL-query,
    it is modified with additional clauses and parameters to match your security rules.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Modification of queries</title>
    <para>
      JPA Security modifies the where-clause of your JPQL queries by adding restrictions
      according to your access rules. This behavior enforces security-rule-evaluation
      within the database. Only database rows resulting in entities that the user is
      allowed to read will be loaded. When using <systemitem>Hibernate</systemitem>
      as persistence provider, the <systemitem>Hibernate</systemitem>-<systemitem>WITH</systemitem>-clause
      is supported by JPA Security.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Secure entities</title>
    <para>
      The proxies that are created around your entities are called <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem>
      (actually they implement an interface of the same name). This is how they behave:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When an entity is accessed for the first time a check is performed whether the current
          user is allowed to read the entity.
        </para>
        <para>
          On the first access of the entity all one-to-one- and many-to-one-relations to other entities
          are replaced by relations to <systemitem>SecureEntities</systemitem> which screen the original entities
          Furthermore one-to-many- and many-to-many-relations are replaced by <systemitem>SecureCollections</systemitem>,
          which are explained later.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Changes to the <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem> are buffered and only flushed to the entity when the active transaction
          is committed. This occurs when <systemitem>flush()</systemitem> is called on the <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>
          or a query is performed with flush-mode <systemitem>AUTO</systemitem> (which is the default).
          As a matter of course whenever a <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem> flushes its changes a check is performed
          whether the current user is allowed to update the entity or not.  
        </para>
        <para>
          During the flush of a <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem> all relations to other <systemitem>SecureEntities</systemitem>
          or to <systemitem>SecureCollections</systemitem> are replaced by their corresponding original.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Secure collections</title>
    <para>
      Collection relationships (i.e. one-to-many- and many-to-many-relations) are handled via <systemitem>SecureCollections</systemitem>.
      Secure collections are filtered in memory and the backing collection will contain every entity of the
      original relationship. The main difference is that when you access any method of a secure collection it will behave, as if it only contained
      those entities you are allowed to read. In addition write-access will only be possible if write-access is allowed to the
      owning entity. Furthermore, for performance reasons every modification to a secure collection is queued and will not be executed until a commit operation.
    </para>  
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Other Operations</title>
    <para>
      Every entity that was loaded over a secured <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem> can be casted to <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem>.
      This interface provides methods to programmatically check accessibility, force read- and write-check
      (via <systemitem>refresh()</systemitem> and <systemitem>flush()</systemitem>) and check the state of the entity.
    </para>
    <para>
      A secure <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem> can be casted to <systemitem>AccessManager</systemitem>, which allows programmatic
      security-checks, too.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>In-Memory evaluation</title>
      <para>
        On every operation that does not result into a query to the database JPA Security tries to check the configured access rules
        in memory. That means, for normal create-, update- and delete-operations, no database interaction is needed <emphasis>for the access check</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        In-memory evaluation works perfectly, when no subselect is contained in the access rules. When the access rules contain
        subselects, some constraints are placed on the definition of the access rules. The first restriction is, that access rules
        that contain subselects may only contain subselects within EXISTS-clauses and not within IN-clauses. This restriction is likely to change in the future.
      </para>
      <para>
        For example the following works:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
GRANT ACCESS TO TestEntity entity WHERE EXISTS (SELECT e FROM TestEntity e WHERE e = entity AND ...)
        ]]>          
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        Whereas the following will not work for the current release:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
GRANT ACCESS TO TestEntity entity WHERE entity IN (SELECT e FROM TestEntity e WHERE ...)
        ]]>          
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        Every subselect that contains only references to pathes to properties of the checked entity will work. 
      </para>
      <para>
        For example the following works, since <systemitem>acl</systemitem> is a direct reference to a property
        of the checked entity (indicated by <systemitem>acl = entity.acl</systemitem>):
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
GRANT ACCESS TO TestEntity entity WHERE EXISTS (SELECT acl FROM AccessControlList acl WHERE acl = entity.acl AND ...)
        ]]>          
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        Whereas the following will not work since there is no direct path from a property of the checked entity to
        <systemitem>e</systemitem> (Reverse navigation would take place from <systemitem>e.acl</systemitem> to
        <systemitem>e</systemitem>, which is currently not supported).
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
GRANT ACCESS TO TestEntity entity WHERE EXISTS (SELECT e FROM AclEntry e WHERE e.acl = entity.acl)
        ]]>          
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        The access rule could be rewritten to work with in-memory evaluation:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
GRANT ACCESS TO TestEntity entity WHERE EXISTS (SELECT e FROM AccessControlList acl JOIN acl.entries e WHERE acl = entity.acl)
        ]]>          
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        When in-memory evaluation cannot take place within the previously defined constraints, there is another chance
        to evaluate a query in memory: When the entities that are needed for the specified evaluation are already loaded
        within the specific <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>, evaluation will take place based on that entities. That means, if
        every <systemitem>AclEntry</systemitem> of the specific entity was loaded into memory by previous operations, the following
        access rule <emphasis>can</emphasis> be evaluated:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        <![CDATA[
GRANT ACCESS TO TestEntity entity WHERE EXISTS (SELECT e FROM AclEntry e WHERE e.acl = entity.acl)
        ]]>          
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        When an access rule cannot be evaluated the access-check will return <systemitem>false</systemitem>.
        <emphasis>This behavior will change in the future since it is not deterministic
        since the evaluation depends on previously loaded entities</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
