<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>How does JPA Security work internally?</title>
  <para>
    JPA Security intercepts your action with the <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>.
    Whenever you retrieve an entity from your <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>,
    it is backed by a proxy from JPA Security and whenever you perform a JPQL-query,
    it is modified with additional clauses and parameters to match your security rules.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Modification of queries</title>
    <para>
      Bla
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Secure entities</title>
    <para>
      The proxies that are created around your entities are called <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem>
      (actually they implement an interface of the same name). This is how they behave:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When the entity is accessed first a check is performed, whether the current
          user is allowed to read the entity.
        </para>
        <para>
          On the first access of the entity all one-to-one- and one-to-many-relations to other entities
          are replaced by relations to <systemitem>SecureEntities</systemitem> that back the original entities
          and all many-to-one- and many-to-many-relations are replaced by <systemitem>SecureCollections</systemitem>,
          which are explained later.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Changes to the entity are buffered and only flushed to the entity when the active transaction
          is committed, <systemitem>flush()</systemitem> is called on the <systemitem>EntityManager</systemitem>
          or a query is performed with flush-mode <systemitem>AUTO</systemitem> (which is the default).
          Whenever a <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem> flushes its changes, a check is performed before,
          whether the current user is allowed to update the entity.  
        </para>
        <para>
          During the flush of a <systemitem>SecureEntity</systemitem> all relations to other <systemitem>SecureEntities</systemitem>
          or to <systemitem>SecureCollections</systemitem> are replaced by their corresponding original.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Secure collections</title>
    <para>
      ...
    </para>  
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Other Operations</title>
    <para>
      ...
    </para>
  </section>
</article>
